Finding Aid for the The Andrew Nelson Lytle 1988 Addition
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Andrew Nelson Lytle 1988 Addition
2005
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0603
Summary
Size 1 linear ft.
Geographic Locations United States
Inclusive Dates 1922-1988
Bulk Dates 1937-1987
Languages English
Summary The Papers of Andrew Nelson Lytle (1902-1995), author, educator, editor, critic and Vanderbilt University alumnus (B.A. 1925), were acquired in 1988 from Mr. Lytle. Lytle was a member of the Agrarian literary movement and was close colleagues with Robert Penn Warren, John Crowe Ransom, and Allen Tate.
Access Restrictions No restrictions
Copyright Andrew Lytle’s literary executor is his son-in-law, George Chamberlain of Sewanee. His address is: George I. Chamberlain 233 Quintard Road Sewanee, TN 37375 Telephone: 931-598-0532
Stack Locations Manuscripts
Biography
Born on December 26, in Murfreesboro, Tennessee, to Robert Logan and Lillie Belle Lytle. 1902
Father buys the Log Cabin at Monteagle, Tennessee 1907
Enrolls in Sewanee Military Academy as a day student in fall of 1916; attends as boarding student after fall of 1917 when mother buys house in Sewanee; wins the Golden Medal for Scholarship; upon graduation is offered, but refuses an appointment to West Point; travels in France with mother and sister, Polly; writes a letter from France to Sewanee’s headmaster, Major Henry Gass, which is printed in The Little Tiger, the student publication; prepares for admission to Oxford while at the home of Mademoiselle Durieux on the Left Bank in Paris with an English tutor; studies fencing. 1916-1920
Enters Exeter College, Oxford; called home after three weeks because of death of grandfather, John Nelson; enrolls in Vanderbilt in fall to be near grandmother, Molly Nelson, in Murfreesboro 1921
Takes sophomore literature under Donald Davidson. 1922
Publishes two poems in Vanderbilt’s undergraduate review, Driftwood Flames, “Hill Cattle” and “Une Reflexion.” 1923
Becomes a student of John Crowe Ransom and a classmate of Robert Penn Warren during Vanderbilt career; writes Journal of European Tour: 1 July – 6 September 1924; attends Fugitive meetings during senior year. 1924
Publishes “Edward Graves” in March issue of The Fugitives; Vanderbilt’s Calumet Club produces his one-act play The Gold Tooth; graduates from Vanderbilt with B.A. degree; goes to Guntersville, Alabama, where he runs his father’s farm, Cornsilk, for a year. 1925
Begins a long play entitled New Ground: raises strawberries; becomes a student of George Pierce Baker at the 47 Workshop at Yale in the fall; wins several acting roles. 1926
Receives an invitation from Tate in March to visit him at 27 Bank Street, New York City; their friendship begins. 1927
Baker’s Experimental Theatre produces his one-act play, The Lost Sheep; earns a role in a twelve-week Broadway production of The Grey Fox. 1928
Lytle does research for a biography of Nathan Bedford Forrest; plans a biography of J.C. Calhoun; lives with paralytic boy as a paid housekeeper; returns to South in May to continue Forrest research; spends June in New York trying out for The Patriarch which open is fall [1926]; becomes involved in plans for an Agrarian offensive. 1929
Contributes “The Hind Tit” to Agrarian symposium; argues against title, I’ll Take My Stand; continues work on Forrest. 1930
Oversees strawberry crop in Huntsville, Alabama; publishes Bedford Forrest and His Critter Company; reviews Stribling’s The Forge in “Life in the Cotton Belt” for New Republic; is reported in July in Huntsville’s The Times to advocate erecting a Forrest statue; returns to Southampton on Long Island in summer where, with George Haight as director and treasurer, he and others start the Hampton Players; in July performs in The Immodest Violet; reviews four Lincoln books for Virginia Quarterly Review in “The Lincoln Myth.” 1931
Publishes first piece of fiction, “Old Scratch in the Valley,” in Virginia Quarterly Review; decides against Calhoun biography; reviews book on Robert Barnwell Rhett and one of Edmund Ruffin for Hound and Horn in “Principles of Secession”; visits Albemarle, Virginia; there becomes engaged to a daughter of the Pattons who, in September, breaks the engagement; gets involved in a legal battle over mortgage rights to Cornsilk; continues to work on long play; begins “Mr. MacGregor.” His mother dies. 1932
Reviews book on Sherman for Virginia Quarterly Review in “A Tactical Blunder”; contributes “A Confederate General” to New Republic; finishes revision of “The Backwoods Progression” and publishes it in American Review. 1933
Receives Owsley’s narrative of his Uncle Dink in June; attends Alabama Writers’ Conference; completes “John Taylor and the Political Economy,” a three-part essay published in American Review; spends Christmas in New Orleans with Tates 1934
Publishes “The Passion of Aleck Maury,” a review of Caroline Gordon’s novel in New Republic; attends the Mercantile Library Association meeting in Cincinnati with Tate; “Mr. MacGregor” appears in Virginia Quarterly Review in April; works on a play, possibly The Gold Dust Family, while at Cornsilk; reviews Chilton’s Follow The Furies and later, Freeman’s R.E. Lee in The Southern Review; begins paper for second agrarian symposium. 1935
Becomes professor of American History at Southwestern College in Memphis; “Jericho, Jericho” appears in The Southern Review; contributes “The Small Farm Secures the State” to Who Owns America?; by August the Alabama Supreme Court decides in favor of his father in the farm lawsuit; “The Approach of the Southern Writer to His Material” appears in The Atlanta Constitution. 1936
Goes to New Orleans in February then on to Hollywood; visits George Haight and investigates movie possibilities; helps wage campaign to retain Ransom at Vanderbilt; begins work on At The Moon’s Inn. 1937
Reviews Styron’s The Cast Iron Man in “John C. Calhoun” for The Southern Review; continues research on De Soto in Nashville and Little Rock; marries Edna Langdon Barker in June; spends three months in California working on novel; moves to Monteagle in fall. 1938
Attends Writers’ Conference in Savannah; continues work on De Soto and publishes excerpt, “A Fragment: How Nuno Tovar Came to Cross the Ocean Sea,” in June; remains at Monteagle but buys a 330-acre farm in Robertson County, Tennessee. 1939
Receives Guggenheim Fellowship; spends part of summer with Tates at Princeton; in December, secures 627 Dumaine Street in New Orleans for three months and works on De Soto. 1940
Gets a three-month extension of Guggenheim; returns to Monteagle around June first; accepts offer of a rent-free house at Sewanee in exchange for public lectures; At The Moon’s Inn appears November 16, the day his first daughter, Pamela, is born. 1941
Accepts a teaching position at Sewanee Military Academy; later becomes professor of history at the University of the South and managing editor of Sewanee Review; “Alchemy” comes out in Kenyon Review. 1942
Reviews Freeman’s Lee’s Lieutenants for Sewanee Review; father dies on Valentine’s Day in Guntersville; sells what remains of Cornsilk after TVA flooding; spends summer at farm in Portland in Robertson County; publishes a review of Warren’s At Heaven’s Gate in Sewanee Review; declines job in war department. 1943
Raises turkeys and tobacco in Portland; continues to edit Review through spring issue; goes on duck hunt to Reelfoot Lake which contributes to the creation of “The Guide.” 1944
“The Guide” (later “The Mahogany Frame”) appears in Sewanee Review and wins Lytle a cash prize from Prentice-Hall. 1945
Remains in Portland and begins work on A Name for Evil; a second daughter, Katherine Anne, is born on May 12. 1946
Goes to University of Iowa for spring semester to take over fiction classes and work on novella; makes a three-day trip to California in April; spends summer in Portland finishing A Name for Evil which comes out in August; returns to Iowa in fall as Acting Head of the Iowa University School of Writing; Flannery O’Connor is in his writing class. 1947
Takes over household chores while Edna recuperates from an operation; attends a ten-day workshop in Missouri in June; returns to Portland; publishes “Note on a Traditional Sensibility,” a tribute to Ransom in Sewanee Review; in fall accepts position of Lecturer in Creative Writing at the University of Florida in Gainesville 1948
Publishes “Regeneration for Man,” an essay on Faulkner’s Intruder in the Dust in Sewanee Review; starts work on what will become The Velvet Horn; sells Log Cabin to the Woman’s Association; begins building a house in Gainesville; assesses Gordon’s fiction in a Sewanee Review essay entitled “Caroline Gordon and the Historic Image.” 1949
Moves into newly finished house at 1822 North West Ave. in May. 1950
Continues work on The Velvet Horn. 1951
Contributes to “The Agrarian Today,” a symposium published in Shenandoah; leases Portland farm. 1952
Submits “How Many Miles to Babylon” to the Hopkins symposium; “Image as the Guide to Meaning in the Historical Novel” appears in Sewanee Review; the third daughter, Lillie Langdon is born November 15. 1953
Heads the humanities division of the International Seminar of the Harvard Summer School; visits the Allen Tates in Princeton; works five weeks on a Faulkner paper; reviews Gerald Carson’s The Old Country Store for The Southern Folklore Quarterly; goes to New York in December to summarize three papers given at the MLA symposium, “The Southern Literary Renaissance.” 1954
Publishes Faulkner essay, “The Son of Man: He Will Prevail,” in Sewanee Review; continues work on The Velvet Horn; his “A Summing Up,” along with the three other papers from the MLA symposium, is published in Shenandoah. 1955
Participates in the Fugitives’ Reunion held at Vanderbilt, May 3-5; “What Quarter of the Night,” an excerpt from The Velvet Horn, still in progress, appears in Sewanee Review; publishes “A Hero and the Doctrinaires of Defeat” in The Georgia Review and an essay on Gordon’s collection of short stories, The Forest of the South, in Critique. 1956
Leaves Bobbs-Merrill for McDowell, Obolensky; sells Portland farm in April; publishes an essay on Faulkner, “The Town: Helen’s Last Stand” in Sewanee Review; The Velvet Horn comes out in August; goes to New York to promote sales. 1957
Reviews works by Walter Sullivan, Howard Nemerov, and Peter Taylor in “The Displaced Family” in Sewanee Review; reviews The Lasting South, ed. by Kilpatrick and Rubin, in “The Quality of the South” for National Review; A Novel, Novella and Four Stories comes out with a new “Foreword”; reviews Cheney’s This Is Adam and Wright’s The Long Dream in “Man or Symbol” for National Review. 1958
“The Working Novelist and the Mythmaking Process” appears in Daedalus; has a serious operation in June which forces him to cancel a summer lectureship at Harvard; attends McDowell, Obolensky anniversary party in New York in August; visits Tate and Isabella at Princeton; publishes “Allen Tate: Upon the Occasion of His Sixtieth Birthday” in Sewanee Review; writes an introduction for a new printing of Forrest; spends Christmas with Tates in Florida. 1959
Funding from Guggenheim Fellowship begins; makes plans to write memoir; travels to Mexico, but Edna becomes ill there; returns to Florida then Memphis where she is diagnosed as having lung cancer; buys back the Log Cabin from the Woman’s Association; the new printing of Forrest appears. 1960
Takes leave of absence from Gainesville in May to edit Sewanee Review and becomes lecturer in English at the University of the South; begins editing Review with Autumn number. 1961
Attends Literary Festival in Spartanburg and ALMA in New York; works on essay on impressionism. 1962
Learns that Edna’s cancer has returned; publishes “Agee’s Letters to Father Flye” in Sewanee Review and “Impressionism, the Ego and the First Person” in Daedalus; is called back to hospital during Vanderbilt’s annual symposium; Edna dies April 26; invites Pamela and her husband, Jim Law, to move in the Log Cabin; fulfills engagements at Richmond, Kentucky, and Tryon, North Carolina, before attending the William Elliott celebration in Cambridge in July. 1963
Undergoes another serious operation in spring; daughter Kate marries in August; delivers Founder’s Day Address, “A Christian University and the Word,” at Sewanee in October; publishes a tribute to Flannery O’Connor in Espirit, the literary magazine of the University of Scranton. 1964
Plans a special issue of the Review devoted to Eliot and guest edited by Tate; is accorded an honorary Doctor of Letters degree from Kenyon; publishes an essay on Hemingway, “A Moveable Feast: The Going To and Fro” and one on Bovary, “In Defense of a Passionate and Incorruptible Heart” in Sewanee Review. 1965
Brings out Eliot issue; participates in a discussion published in Alabama Alumni News as “And Like All Good Conversations It Never Ends”; adds “’The Open Boat’: A Pagan Tale” to the essays collected and published as The Hero with the Private Parts; receives the National Foundation for the Arts and Humanities Award. 1966
“A Wake for the Living” appears in Sewanee Review as an excerpt from a memoir by that name, still in progress. 1967
Attends Dallas Literary Festival honoring Nashville Agrarians and presents paper on Joyce; promoted to rank of Professor of English at University of the South. 1968
A Name for Evil appears an unauthorized Avon Paperback; “A Reading of Joyce’s ‘The Dead’” printed in Sewanee Review; adds “Forward” to a collection of Owsley’s essays, The South: Old and New Frontiers. 1969
Accorded honorary Doctor of Letters degree by University of Florida during Florida’s Writers’ Conference; “Jericho, Jericho, Jericho” is dramatized at Vanderbilt. 1970
“The Garden of Innocence,” a second excerpt from The Wake and “The State of Letters in a Time of Disorder” appear in Sewanee Review; edits and prepares “Forward” to Craft and Vision: The Best Fiction from “The Sewanee Review.” 1971
“The Old Neighborhood,” a third excerpt from the memoir in progress, appears in The Southern Review. 1972
A surreptitious Avon Paperback of The Long Night comes out in March; retires as editor of Sewanee Review with the Autumn issue; accorded honorary Doctor of Letters degree from University of the South. 1973
Serves as Vanderbilt’s Visiting Professor during spring semester. 1974
Moves to a 75-acre farm in Kentucky in April; A Wake for the Living appears in July; a response to questions is recorded in South Dakota Review as “The Writer’s Sense of Place.” 1975
Composes a tribute to Peter Taylor, “On a Birthday,” for Shenandoah. Sells the Kentucky farms and moves back to the Log Cabin. 1976
Writes “A Ploughman’s Politics” on the republication of John Taylor of Caroline’s Arator for Modern Age. 1977
Prepares an “Introduction” for the Palaemon Press’s limited edition of Alchemy; contributes “The Momentary Man” to The Hillsdale Review, a publication of Hillsdale College, Michigan. 1978
Publishes “They Took Their Stand: The Agrarian View After Fifty Years” in Modern Age and, separately, as Reflections of a Ghost; contributes an untitled response to the question “Is Regional Writing Dead?” for The Student, a publication of Wake Forest University; publishes a reminiscence, “A Journey South,” in Kentucky Review; attends Vanderbilt’s Fiftieth Anniversary of the Agrarian Manifesto; participates in a discussion published as “The Agrarian-Industrial Metaphor” in A Band of Prophets, ed. by Harvard and Sullivan; writes “A Tribute” for the Katherine Anne Porter entry in the 1980 Yearbook of Dictionary of Literary Biography. 1979
Publishes “The Artists in a Time of Disorder” in The Chattahoochee Review; “A Partial Reading of Parade’s End or the Hero as an Old Furniture Dealer” in The Presence of Ford Madox Ford; “The Search for Order in American Society: The Southern Response” in The Southern Partisan; the “Afterword” to Why The South Will Survive; and “A Tribute” for the Caroline Gordon entry in the 1981 Yearbook of Dictionary of Literary Biography. 1980
Nominated for the Presidential Medal of Freedom; honored at a celebration of his eightieth birthday at Sewanee; The Velvet Horn is reprinted; “Allen Tate and John Peale Bishop” appears in Grand Street; “Recollection and Reflection” appears in Mountain Voices: The Centennial History of the Monteagle Sunday School Assembly. 1981
Adds a personal perspective on Frances Cheney in References Services and Library Education: Essays in Honor of Frances Neel Cheney. 1982
Alchemy and Other Stories published; Bedford Forrest reprinted: “Three Ways of Making a Saint: A Reading of ‘Three Tales” by Flaubert” appears in Southern Review; Katherine Anne Liggett, Lytle’s daughter, dies in Pensacola. 1983
Writes “Foreword” to Shakespeare’s Insistent Theme, a volume in honor of Charles Harrison. Wins the Lynhurst Foundation grant. 1984
Awarded the Ingersoll Foundation prize, the Richard M. Weaver Award for Scholarly Letters given in Chicago in November. Continues to live in the Log Cabin at Monteagle. 1985
Lytle dies in his Monteagle cabin at the age of 92 on December 14, from an illness he had for many years. He was the last surviving member of the Agrarian literary group. 1986
Scope and Contents
The Papers of Andrew Nelson Lytle (1902-1995), author, educator, editor, critic and Vanderbilt University alumnus (B.A. 1925), were acquired in 1988 from Mr. Lytle. A preliminary organization was performed on the collection in 1988, but until now had not been fully processed. This collection consists of copied material and is valued for its informational content such as extensive letters from Lytle’s wife, Edna Langdon Barker Lytle. Included within this collection is correspondence, writings, writings about Lytle, family documents, and financial documents.
For details of Lytle’s life and works, the following are recommended:
Lucas, Mark. “Andrew Lytle,” in Fifty Southern Writers After 1900. Joseph M. Flora and Robert Bain, eds. New York: Greenwood Press, 1987. (Pages 290-300)
Lytle, Andrew Nelson. A Wake For The Living: A Family Chronicle. New York: Crown Publishers, 1975.
Polk, Noel. “Andrew Nelson Lytle: A Biography of His Writings,” Mississippi Quarterly 23 (Fall, 1970): 435-491
Wright, Stuart T. Andrew Nelson Lytle: A Bibliography, 1920-1982. Sewanee, TN: University of the South, 1982.
- SERIES AND SUBSERIES DESCRIPTIONS
  - Series I. Correspondence, 1922 – 1988; The Correspondence Series is contained in 2 boxes of this collection. The series is subdivided into Outgoing (1937–1958) and Incoming (1922–1988). The Outgoing Correspondence is comprised of 71 letters that are arranged chronologically. The date of the postmark was used when a letter was undated. The majority of outgoing correspondence is to Lytle’s wife, Edna Langdon Barker Lytle. There are three undated outgoing letters without postmarked envelopes. The Incoming Correspondence is made up of 582 letters and is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Letters were arranged chronologically when more than one letter of a correspondent was present. As with the outgoing correspondence, the incoming correspondence used the postmark date of the envelope if the letter was undated. The affiliation of the correspondent is noted in parenthesis. Bracketed information indicates either to whom the correspondence is directed if other than Andrew Lytle or gives additional details about the correspondence. Dates are inclusive dates of the correspondence. There are several letters from Edna Langdon Barker Lytle, Andrew’s wife.
  - Series II. Writings, Undated, Writings by Andrew Lytle make up seven folders within this collection. All writings are typescript essays.
  - Series III. Writings About Lytle, Undated, This series is comprised of four folders that are writings about Andrew Lytle or his writings.
  - Series IV. Family, 1959; The family series contains one folder of a grade report for Pamela Lytle at St. Mary’s School in Sewanee, Tennessee.
  - Series V. Financial, 1982 - 1988; There is only one folder that makes up the financial series. The folder consists of various financial documents, such as bills, a royalty statement, a reprint permission fee form, a receipt, and a purchase order from Austin Peay State University.
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Outgoing Correspondence:, March 16, 1937 – July 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence:, Aug. 1, 1939 – March 20, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence:, March 21, 1942 – June 30, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence:, July 6, 1949 – June 21, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence:, June 22, 1954 - Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Alexander, L. – Ashby, J (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Ball, B – Barker, H.H (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Barker, Mrs. H.H. (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Barker, Mrs. H.H. (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Barrett, J. – Bovenizer, D (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Bragg, J. – Bryant, J (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Cardineau, T. – Cullen, C (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Dalrymple, A. – Dunlap, B (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Easterly, J. – England, B (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Farrer, L. – Frederickson, A (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Gardner, I. – Green, F (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Hale, P. – Hunt, S (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Jacobs, M. – Jordan, M (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Kirk, R. – Koch, C (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Law, P. – Lyman, G (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Lytle, E. (1 of 15) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Lytle, E. (2 of 15) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Lytle, E. (3 of 15) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Lytle, E. (4 of 15) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Incoming Correspondence:, Lytle, E. (5 of 15) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (6 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (7 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (8 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (9 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (10 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (11 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (12 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (13 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (14 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, E. (15 of 15) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Lytle, P. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Incoming Correspondence: McConnell, T. – McGehee, L. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Incoming Correspondence: McNabb, T. – Murrah, J. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Nagel, E. – Northouse, C. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Owsley, H. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Paine, J.H.E. – Pritchard, B. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Rasheed, N. – Ryan, S. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Salaita, G. – Sundahle, D. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Tate, A. – Tullis, D. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Underwood, T. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Vanzandt, K. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Walsh, M. – Weeks, L. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Weyman, B. – Wyatt, R. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Yoken, M. – Young, T.D. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Incoming Correspondence: Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 25)
- SERIES II. WRITINGS